Guide to the Marvin Leiner Papers TAM.607
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marvin Leiner Papers
1960-2004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Leiner, Marvin
TAM.607
50 Linear Feet in 40 record cartons, 2 OS flat boxes, 3 media boxes, 3 small flat boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 4 manuscript boxes, 1 card box, and 3 film cans
216 audiocassettes
208 sound tape reels
3 film reels
47.52 Megabytes in 132 floppy disks
Marvin Leiner is a scholar of Cuban education and the author of several books on educational reforms in the wake of the Cuban Revolution. The collection primarily consists of research Leiner conducted while living in Cuba during the 1968-1969 school year and during his many return visits in the 1970s and 1980s. Collection materials consist of reel-to-reel audio tapes, audiocassette tapes, slides, photographs, film reels, diaries, field notes, newspaper clippings, microfilm, floppy disks, transcripts of interviews, correspondence, and early manuscript drafts. A majority of the collection materials contain Leiner's research on Cuban education, sexual politics, and healthcare. A small portion of the collection contains Leiner's research regarding education in Nicaragua and China, as well his files for correpsondence, manuscript drafts, and speaking engagements. The Marvin Leiner Papers date from 1960 to 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Marvin Leiner in 2012. The accession number associated with this gift is 2012.018
Appraisal
Documents with sensitive information were found while processing the collection. These documents have been removed from the collection and deaccessioned.
Arrangement
This collection has been organized into three series: Series I: Research Files; Series II: Writings and Correspondence; Series III: Unprocessed Audiovisual and Born-Digital Media. Series I: Research Files has been further organized into three subseries.
The contents of each series and subseries have not been physically arranged by an archivist and the materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Marvin Leiner is the author of several books on sexual politics, education, and childcare in Cuba. Much of his research comes from interviews he conducted and diaries he kept while living in Cuba for the 1968-1969 school year and subsequent trips he made in the 1970s and 1980s. Leiner taught for many years in the Bedford Stuyvesant and Bushwick sections of Brooklyn. He has a Ph.D. in Elementary Education from New York University, and he has lectured in Latin American Studies at Yale and was a Fellow of Yale's Trumbull College.
Leiner's best known book, Sexual Politics in Cuba: Machismo, Homosexuality, and AIDS, analyzes the Cuban practice of quarantining individuals with HIV in the context of the Cuban Revolution. The book also examines the social and educational effects of the Cuban government's intolerance of homosexuality and the efforts by Cuban educators to introduce sex education in schools. Leiner's research interests also include other education reforms in the wake of the Cuban Revolution, particularly the Escuela al Campo (School to the Countryside) program, which incorporated literacy, sports, and cultural programs into agricultural work in the countryside. His other works on the topic of education include Children Are the Revolution: Daycare in Cuba and Children of the Cities: Education of the Powerless, which he edited. Leiner is a Professor Emeritus of Education at Queens College, City University of New York.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains Marvin Leiner's extensive research on Cuban education, sexual politics, and health care, conducted in the late 1960s through the 1990s. His research materials consist of of reel-to-reel audio tapes, audiocassette tapes, slides, photographs, film reels, diaries, field notes from school visits, newspaper clippings, microfilm, floppy disks, and transcripts of interviews with Cuban educators, psychologists, administrators from the Ministry of Education, and other professionals. To a much lesser extent, the collection also includes Leiner's research on education and literacy programs in China and Nicaragua. Research materials date from 1961 to 2001.
The collection also contains files from Leiner's speaking engagements, early working manuscripts of his published works, and correspondence. These materials date from 1967 to 2004.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Materials
Approximately 5.5 linear feet of books and periodicals on Cuban politics, gender issues, education, and healthcare were separated for library cataloging. Some personal papers and photographs were returned to the donor.
Education -- Cuba.; Public health -- Cuba.; Sex role -- Cuba.; Cuba -- Social conditions.; Cuba -- History -- Revolution, 1959.; Education -- Nicaragua.; Education -- China.; Leiner, Marvin
- Series I: Research Files, 1961-2001; 27.5 Linear Feet in 26 record cartons, 2 flat boxes, and 1 manuscript legal box
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Research Files contains Leiner's research materials on education, sexual politics, and health care in Cuba, Nicaragua, and China. A majority of the research files contain research created by Leiner during his trips to Cuba, including his diaries and field notes documenting his visits, photographs of school children and education professionals, and interviews with Cuban educators, psychologists, administrators, and other professionals. The research files also contain newspaper clippings, conference programs and notes, and scholarly publications Leiner gathered covering topics regarding Cuban education, health care, early childhood, gay rights, women's rights, and economic policies. A smaller portion of the research files contain Leiner's field notes and interviews from his trip to Nicaragua, and newspaper clippings and booklets regarding education and health care in Nicaragua and China.
  Arrangement
  Series I: Research Files has been organized into three subseries: Subseries I.A: Cuba; Subseries I.B: Nicaragua; Subseries I.C: China. The materials within Series I are physically arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
  - Subseries I.A: Cuba, 1961-2001
    - Newspaper clippings, 1963-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1-31)
    - Education and political research files, 1963-1982 (Box 1, Folder 37-50, 59-70)
    - Interview transcripts, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 51-52)
    - Research notes, 1963-1982 (Box 1, Folder 32-36, 53-58)
    - Education and media research files, 1969-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1-7, 9-11, 13-43, 47-67)
    - Interviews, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8, 68-70)
    - Notebook, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Campo questionnaire and notes, 1969-1983 (Box 2, Folder 44-46, 71-77)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Education research files, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 3-9, 11-43, 45-63)
    - Interview transcripts, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10, 44, 64)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1-18, 31-32)
    - Education research files, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 19-30)
    - Interview transcripts, 1968-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1-5, 7-23, 41-43)
    - Fidel speeches and interviews, 1977-1985 (Box 5, Folder 24-35)
    - Education, political, and economy research files, 1969-1980 (Box 5, Folder 36-40, 44-53, 56-65)
    - Research notes, 1969-1980 (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
    - Education and early childhood research files, 1978-1984 (Box 6, Folder 1-15, 24-25)
    - Interview transcripts, 1970-1983 (Box 6, Folder 16-21, 26-36)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1971-1984 (Box 6, Folder 22-23)
    - Interview transcripts, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
    - Newspaper clippings and journal articles, 1997-2001 (Box 7, Folder 11-27)
    - Education research files, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Cuban Literacy Campaign research files, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Helms-Burton Conference, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1984 (Box 8, Folder 4-10)
    - Diary, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Economy research files, 1977-1982 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Education research files, 1970-1973 (Box 8, Folder 21-22, 25-26, 58-62)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 27-36)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1979-1989 (Box 9, Folder 34-40, 59-62)
    - Gay rights research files and notes, 1983-1989 (Box 9, Folder 41-58, 65-67)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 63-64)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 1, 20)
    - Education and early childhood research files, 1969-1972 (Box 10, Folder 2-19, 21-32)
    - Field notes and diary, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1975-1988 (Box 11, Folder 1, 10-14)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1986 (Box 11, Folder 2, 18-20)
    - Sex education research files, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Diary and field notes, 1969-1984 (Box 11, Folder 4-6, 16-17, 21)
    - Education research files, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
    - Diary and field notes, 1969-1971 (Box 12, Folder 1-4, 10-13)
    - Education and early childhood research files, 1969-1984 (Box 12, Folder 5-9, 21-22, 25, 28-29)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1977-1994 (Box 12, Folder 16-19, 27)
    - Research notes, 1971-1980 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Interview research and transcripts, 1971-1988 (Box 13, Folder 1-2, 13-14)
    - Diaries and field notes, 1969-1986 (Box 13, Folder 3-8)
    - Education and early childhood research files, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1975-1982 (Box 13, Folder 19-20)
    - Photographs, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 21-22)
    - Education and early childhood research files, 1971-1985 (Box 14, Folder 2-3, 5-15, 30)
    - Diary and field notes, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 31-32)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1971 (Box 14, Folder 33-40)
    - Education and policy research files, 1974-1981 (Box 14, Folder 41-58)
    - Education research files, 1974-1981 (Box 46, Folder 59)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Notebook, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 5-6, 16)
    - Newspaper clippings and journal articles, 1963-1988 (Box 15, Folder 7-14)
    - Education research files, 1971-1981 (Box 15, Folder 17-21)
    - Pedagogy Conference report and notes, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 3-5)
    - Education research files, 1969-1986 (Box 16, Folder 6-9, 11-15)
    - Notebooks, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Conference programs and reports, 1970-1986 (Box 17, Folder 1-8)
    - Diary and notes, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Health and education research files, 1972-1982 (Box 17, Folder 10-14)
    - Health and education research files, 1969-2001 (Box 18, Folder 9-14)
    - Health and education research files, 1968-1997 (Box 19, Folder 1-6, 9-10)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Research notes, 1994-1995 (Box 19, Folder 11-12)
    - Education, AIDS, and women's rights research files, 1989-2001 (Box 20, Folder 2-7)
    - Education research files, 1961-1969 (Box 21, Folder 11-13)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1971 (Box 21, Folder 14-21)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1988 (Box 22, Folder 1-3, 33-36)
    - Education, health, and economy research files, 1973-1989 (Box 22, Folder 4-14, 19-29)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 22, Folder 30-32)
    - Education research files, 1972-1984 (Box 23, Folder 1-7, 27)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984-1987 (Box 23, Folder 8-11)
    - Photographs, 1968-1980 (Box 23, Folder 12-26)
    - Interview transcripts, 1969-1986 (Box 24, Folder 1-3, 27-28)
    - Education and economy research files, 1968-1985 (Box 24, Folder 4-10, 17-22, 29-37)
    - Cuban films research files, 1973-1989 (Box 24, Folder 11-16)
    - Cuban Literacy Campaign research files and notes, 1961-1985 (Box 24, Folder 23-26, 38-42)
    - Research notes, 1984-1988 (Box 24, Folder 43-44)
    - Kenny Leiner's school notes, 1968-1969 (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
    - Education, economy, and political research files, 1961-1986 (Box 25, Folder 4-42)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1970-1971 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Interview transcripts, 1983-1984 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Bibliography index cards, undated (Box 27, Folder 1-14)
    - Notebook, 1994 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984-1987 (Box 27, Folder 16-18)
    - Children's artwork, 1960-1969 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Cuban magazines, 1973-1974 (Box 28, Folder 2-6)
  - Subseries I.B: Nicaragua, 1980-1983
    - Nicaragua Literacy Campaign research files, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 1-6, 19-23)
    - Field notes, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 7-11)
    - Interview transcripts, undated (Box 9, Folder 12-18)
    - Education research files, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 24-33)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Field notes, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 16-17)
    - Field notes, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 1, 7)
    - Nicaragua Literacy Campaign research files, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 2-6)
    - Booklets and pamphlets, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 8-10)
  - Subseries I.C: China, 1972-1976
    - Education research files and notes, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 68-73)
    - Medical information booklets, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 14)
- Series II: Writings and Correspondence, 1967-2004; 14.5 Linear Feet in 14 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
  Series II: Writings and Correspondence contains Leiner's manuscript drafts for his published works, notes and drafts for his speaking engagements, and correspondence regarding grants, publications, and travel arrangements.
  The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
  - Book proposals, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cuba correspondence, 1993-1995 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Paradoxes in Cuban Education article drafts and speech notes, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 13-20)
  - Cuba correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 23-24, 37-57)
  - Children are the Revolution Appendix, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - The Transparent Blackboard, Looking at Cuba Through the Classroom outlines, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Looking at Cuba Through the Schools outlines, undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Appendix drafts, undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Nicaragua speech drafts and notes, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Cuba correspondence, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Conference notes and lecture drafts, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript drafts, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with publishers, 1974-1979 (Box 13, Folder 15-18)
  - General correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript drafts, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Grant information and correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 14, Folder 16-29)
  - Manuscript drafts, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-2, 23-24)
  - Cuba conference notes and lecture drafts, 1974-1979 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Outlines and bibliographies, undated (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Queens College correspondence and publications, 1999-2004 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - A Study of Cuban Education report and notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Sexual Politics in Cuba manuscript drafts, 1990-1991 (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
  - Townsend High School Founder's Day speeches and notes, 2001-2002 (Box 18, Folder 7-8)
  - Israel lecture correspondence and notes, 1994-1995 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - General correspondence, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Blank postcards, undated (Box 19, Folder 13-14)
  - Queens College correspondence, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Lecture correspondence, research, and notes, 1989-2003 (Box 20, Folder 8-13)
  - Queens College correspondence, 1968-1989 (Box 22, Folder 15-17)
  - Travel, grants, and conference correspondence, 1967-1978 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - Manuscripts drafts, 1971 (Box 23, Folder 28)
  - Queens College correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 26, Folder 10-11)
  - General correspondence, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 12-13)
  - Cuba correspondence, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 14)
- Series III: Unprocessed Audiovisual and Born-Digital Media, 1960-1989; 16 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons; 216 audiocassettes; 208 sound tape reels; 2 film reels; 47.52 Megabytes in 132 floppy disks
  Scope and Content Note
  Series III: Unprocessed Audiovisual and Born-Digital Media contains media created by Leiner during his research trips and while writing his manuscripts. Materials consist of audiocassette tapes, open reel audio tapes, open reel film, microfilm, floppy disks, slides, and photographs.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Audiovisual and born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
  - Slides, 1983-1986 (Box 49)
  - Photographs, 1983-1986 (Box 29)
  - Slides, 1968-1980 (Box 30)
  - Slides, 1980 (Box 31, Box 50, Box 51)
  - Audiocassette tapes, 1986-1989 (Box 32)
  - Slides, 1968-1984 (Box 33)
  - Open reel audio tapes, undated (Box 34)
  - Photographs, 1983-1984 (Box 34)
  - Audiocassette tapes, 1983-1984 (Box 34)
  - Microfilm, undated (Box 57)
  - Open reel audio tapes, undated (Box 35, Film 40)
  - Open reel audio tapes, 1960-1971 (Box 36)
  - Open reel audio tapes, 1967-1971 (Box 37, Box 52)
  - Open reel audio tapes, 1968-1969 (Box 38, Box 53)
  - Audiocassette tapes, 1980-1984 (Box 39)
  - Floppy disks, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 130)
  - Slides, 1968-1979 (Box 41, Box 54)
  - Audiocassette tapes, 1968-1979 (Box 41, Box 54)
  - Open reel audio tapes, undated (Box 42)
  - Open reel film, undated (Film 55, Film 56)
  - Audiocassette tapes, 1983-1984 (Box 43, Box 47)
  - Photographs, 1983-1984 (Box 48)
  - Slides, 1983-1984 (Box 48)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 45)
  - Slides, undated (Box 44, Box 45)